Register of the Archives of the Soviet communist party and Soviet state microfilm collection: Russian State Archive of Contemporary History (Rossiiskii gosudarstvennyi arkhiv noveishei istorii - RGANI)
Hoover Institution Archives
- Fond 89, Communist Party of the Soviet Union on Trial records, 1919-1992; 24 reels (Reel 1.989-1.1012)
  - Opis 5
    - Resolution of the TsK KPSS Secretariat on establishing a joint venture with the Khanza-Turist Company (Federal Republic of Germany), 1990 August (Opis 5, Reel 1.989, File 3)
    - Resolution of the TsK KPSS on transferring buildings of historical and cultural significance occupied by the Administration of TsK KPSS Affairs to the Soviet Cultural Foundation; memorandum from the Ideology Department, from the Department for Liaison with Socio-Political Organizations, and from the KPSS Committee of the TsK KPSS apparatus, 1990 September (Opis 5, Reel 1.989, File 4)
    - Resolution of the TsK KPSS Secretariat on the working visit of O. Shenin, Secretary of the TsK KPSS, to Cuba, 1990 October (Opis 5, Reel 1.989, File 5)
    - Resolution of the TsK KPSS Secretariat on providing living expenses and housing to correspondents of communist and social democratic newspapers of capitalist and developing countries; memorandum from the International Department and the Administration of TsK KPSS Affairs, 1990 November (Opis 5, Reel 1.989, File 6)
    - Resolution of the TsK KPSS Secretariat on measures to be taken in connection with the 4th Congress of People's Deputies of the USSR; list of scheduled measures with indication of responsible TsK KPSS departments, 1990 December (Opis 5, Reel 1.989, File 7)
    - Resolution of the TsK KPSS Secretariat on reorganization of the network of correspondents representing Soviet central newspapers and on their financing; memorandum from the Ideology Department and the Administration of TsK KPSS Affairs, 1990 December (Opis 5, Reel 1.989, File 8)
    - Resolution of the TsK KPSS Secretariat on the preparation of the TsK KPSS Plenary Session re the activities of communists in the USSR Soviets of People's Deputies; list of scheduled measures, 1991 January (Opis 5, Reel 1.989, File 9)
    - Resolution of the TsK KPSS Secretariat on the expenses allowed to representatives of the TsK KPSS and the Central Control Commission (TsKK) of the KPSS during trips to the Baltic republics; memorandum to the TsK KPSS from the Administration of TsK KPSS Affairs and the Organizational Department, 1991 January (Opis 5, Reel 1.989, File 10)
    - Resolution of the TsK KPSS Secretariat on letters and telegrams responding to the situation in the Baltic republics, 1991 January (Opis 5, Reel 1.989, File 11)
    - Resolution of the TsK KPSS Secretariat on the information of TsK KPSS departments about the situation in the Baltic republics; memorandum to the TsK KPSS from the Department of National Policy and the Organizational Department, 1991 February (Opis 5, Reel 1.989, File 12)
    - Resolution of the TsK KPSS Secretariat on the party conference of the Western Group of Troops of the Soviet Armed Forces, 1991 March (Opis 5, Reel 1.989, File 13)
    - Extract from minutes of the TsK KPSS Secretariat re permission to export copies of archival documents to the United States, 1991 March (Opis 5, Reel 1.989, File 14)
    - Resolution of the TsK KPSS Secretariat allowing the deposit of 50,000,000 rubles from the Party insurance trust into the account of the Rossiia commercial bank at the request of the KPSS Committee of Leningradskaia oblast (obkom), 1991 April (Opis 5, Reel 1.989, File 15)
    - Resolution of the TsK KPSS Secretariat on cooperation with the F. Ebert Foundation (Federal Republic of Germany) to provide training to experts in the area of managerial and financial activities of the KPSS; memorandum to the TsK KPSS from the Administration of TsK KPSS Affairs and the departments of the TsK KPSS, 1991 March (Opis 5, Reel 1.989, File 16)
    - Resolution of the TsK KPSS Secretariat re legislation on private property and privatization in the Russian Federation; memorandum to the TsK KPSS from P. Luchinskii, O. Baklanov, and A. V. Vlasov, 1991 March (Opis 5, Reel 1.989, File 17)
    - Resolution of the TsK KPSS Secretariat on measures to be taken re the TsK KPSS Politburo resolution Political Results of the Referendum in the USSR and Main Tasks of the Party Organizations; list of measures to be taken by the TsK KPSS Secretariat, 1991 April (Opis 5, Reel 1.989, File 18)
    - Resolution of the TsK KPSS Secretariat on amendments to the instructions to be sent to KPSS organizations of the Soviet Armed Forces, 1991 May (Opis 5, Reel 1.989, File 19)
    - Resolution of the TsK KPSS Secretariat on improvements in the managerial and economic activities of the party organs, 1991 June (Opis 5, Reel 1.989, File 20)
    - Resolution of the TsK KPSS Secretariat on the problems re rehabilitation of repressed peoples; memorandum to the TsK KPSS from the Department of National Policy, 1991 June (Opis 5, Reel 1.989, File 21)
    - Resolution of the TsK KPSS Secretariat on the ideological and theoretical education of communists in the new political situation, 1991 June (Opis 5, Reel 1.989, File 22)
    - Resolution of the TsK KPSS Secretariat on the situation in the workers' movement and the goals of local party organizations, 1991 June (Opis 5, Reel 1.989, File 23)
    - Resolution of the TsK KPSS Secretariat on the convocation of the TsK KPSS Plenary Meeting, 1991 July (Opis 5, Reel 1.989, File 24)
    - Resolution of the TsK KPSS Secretariat on the schedule of TsK KPSS Secretariat activities in July-September 1991; list of scheduled steps, 1991 July (Opis 5, Reel 1.989, File 25)
    - Resolution of the TsK KPSS Secretariat on scheduled meetings in the TsK KPSS with representatives of communist and leftist parties of Latin America, 1991 July (Opis 5, Reel 1.989, File 26)
  - Opis 6
    - Extract from the minutes of the TsK KPSS Presidium re the draft letter On Strengthening Political Work of Party Organization with the Masses and on Stopping the Activities of Anti-Soviet, Hostile Elements to be sent to the central committees of the communist parties of the union republics, and to the KPSS committees in krais and oblasts (kraikoms and obkoms); the draft letter; cover letter to the TsK KPSS Presidium, signed by L. Brezhnev, G. Malenkov, A. Aristov, N. Beliaev, I. Serov, and R. Rudenko, 1956 December (Opis 6, Reel 1.989, File 1)
    - Extract from the minutes of the TsK KPSS Presidium approving the draft letter On Strengthening Political Work of Party Organization with the Masses and on Stopping the Activities of Anti-Soviet, Hostile Elements; final text of the letter, 1956 December (Opis 6, Reel 1.989, File 2)
    - Memorandum to N. Khrushchev, First Secretary of the TsK KPSS, from F. Kozlov, First Secretary of the KPSS Committee of Leningradskaia oblast (obkom), re ideological issues, 1956 December (Opis 6, Reel 1.989, File 3)
    - Memorandum to N. Khrushchev, First Secretary of the TsK KPSS, from F. Kozlov, First Secretary of the KPSS Committee of Leningradskaia oblast (obkom), re the response to the memorandum, 1957 January (Opis 6, Reel 1.989, File 4)
      See also files 1 and 2 of this opis.
    - Memorandum to the TsK KPSS from V. Churaev, Chief of the Department of Administrative Organs, re anti-party speeches at the meetings of local party organizations made while discussing the letter from the TsK KPSS, 1957 February (Opis 6, Reel 1.989, File 5)
    - Memorandum to the TsK KPSS from V. Churaev, Chief of the Department of Administrative Organs; memorandum with additional information re anti-party speeches at the meetings of local party organizations made while discussing the memorandum from the TsK KPSS, 1957 February (Opis 6, Reel 1.989, File 6)
    - Memorandum to the TsK KPSS from P. Ivashutin, Deputy Chairman of the Committee for State Security (KGB), re arrest of anti-Soviet scholars from Moscow State University (L. Krasnopevtsev, N. Obushenkov, L. Rendel, Pokrovskii, V. Kozovoi) and investigation of their activity, 1957 September (Opis 6, Reel 1.989, File 7)
    - File is unavailable, 1918-1991 (Opis 6, Reel 1.989, File 8)
    - Report to R. Malinovskii, Minister of Defense, from Marshal S. Biriuzov re anti-Soviet leaflets found near the Moscow suburb Balashikha; map, attached to the report, 1959 April (Opis 6, Reel 1.989, File 9)
    - Extract from the minutes of the TsK KPSS Presidium re the situation at the construction site of the metallurgical plant in Karaganda, 1959 October (Opis 6, Reel 1.989, File 10)
    - Report to the TsK KPSS from P. Ivashutin, Deputy Chairman of the KGB, re reaction of the USSR population to the increase in the retail prices of meat, meat products, and butter, 1962 June (Opis 6, Reel 1.989, File 11)
    - Report to the TsK KPSS from V. Semichastnyi, Chairman of the Committee for State Security (KGB), re reaction of the USSR population to the increase in the retail prices of meat, meat products, and butter, 1962 June 2 (Opis 6, Reel 1.989, File 12)
    - Report to the TsK KPSS from V. Semichastnyi, Chairman of the KGB, re reaction of the USSR population to the increase in the retail prices of meat, meat products, and butter, 1962 June (Opis 6, Reel 1.989, File 13)
    - Report to the TsK KPSS from V. Semichastnyi, Chairman of the KGB, re reaction of the USSR population to the increase in the retail prices of meat, meat products, and butter, 1962 June 3 (Opis 6, Reel 1.989, File 14)
    - Live radio appeal of F. Kozlov to the citizens of the city of Novocherkassk re disturbances of workers in city plants, 1962 April (Opis 6, Reel 1.989, File 15)
    - Report to the TsK KPSS from P. Ivashutin, Deputy Chairman of the KGB, on the disturbances in Novocherkassk, 1962 June (Opis 6, Reel 1.989, File 16)
    - Report to the TsK KPSS from V. Semichastnyi, Chairman of the KGB, re the situation in Novocherkassk after suppression of the disturbances, and the number of casualties, 1962 June (Opis 6, Reel 1.989, File 17)
    - Report to N. Khrushchev from V. Semichastnyi, Chairman of the KGB, presenting biographical data on the people killed during, and arrested in connection with, the disturbances in Novocherkassk, 1962 June (Reel 1.989, File 18)
    - Report to the TsK KPSS (June 13, 1962) from V. Semichastnyi, Chairman of the KGB, and R. Rudenko, Prosecutor General, re charges against participants in the disturbances and the request for an open trial against them; handwritten note, stating that the report had been discussed at the TsK KPSS Presidium meeting but that the discussion was not supposed to be reflected in the minutes; draft text of the indictment to be brought against the participants in the Novocherkassk disturbances [before the trial], 1962 July (Opis 6, Reel 1.989, File 19)
    - Extract from the minutes of the TsK KPSS Presidium re the draft resolution of the USSR Council of Ministers and the draft directives of the Committee for State Security (KGB) and the Prosecutor General on intensification of the struggle against anti-Soviet elements; the draft resolution; the draft directive of the KGB; the draft directive of the Prosecutor General; memorandum to the TsK KPSS from the leaders of the USSR Council of Ministers, Committee for State Security (KGB), and Prosecutor General's Office, 1962 July (Opis 6, Reel 1.989, File 20)
    - Memorandum to the TsK KPSS from V. Semichastnyi, Chairman of the KGB, re increase in the number of anti-Soviet leaflets distributed in different locations of the USSR, 1962 July (Opis 6, Reel 1.989, File 21)
    - The first page of the memorandum presented in file 21, 1962 July (Opis 6, Reel 1.989, File 22)
    - Report to the TsK KPSS from P. Ivashutin, Deputy Chairman of the KGB, submitting information on the trial of the participants in the disturbances in Novocherkassk and on the situation in the city, 1962 August (Opis 6, Reel 1.989, File 23)
    - Report to the TsK KPSS from P. Ivashutin, Deputy Chairman of the KGB, and R. Rudenko, Prosecutor General, on the completion of the trial of the participants in the disturbances in Novocherkassk, 1962 August (Opis 6, Reel 1.989, File 24)
    - Memorandum to the TsK KPSS from V. Stepakov, Chief of the Propaganda Department, re the trial in Novocherkassk; N. Khrushchev's handwritten request to pass on the memorandum to the TsK members and candidate members and to the TsK Secretaries, 1962 August (Opis 6, Reel 1.989, File 25)
    - Note from Malenkov requesting that a document (unidentified) be passed on to the members and candidate members of the TsK KPSS Presidium, 1963 November (Opis 6, Reel 1.989, File 26)
    - Memorandum to the TsK KPSS from V. Titov re incidents that occurred during the celebration of the 46th anniversary of the October revolution in different locations of the USSR, 1963 November (Opis 6, Reel 1.989, File 27)
    - Memorandum to the TsK KPSS from V. Semichastnyi, Chairman of the KGB, re distribution of anti-Soviet leaflets in different locations of the USSR, 1965 August (Opis 6, Reel 1.989, File 28)
    - Memorandum to the TsK KPSS from V. Semichastnyi, Chairman of the KGB, re nationalistic actions in the Kazakh Republic, 1965 December (Opis 6, Reel 1.989, File 29)
    - Memorandum to the TsK KPSS from V. Semichastnyi, Chairman of the KGB, re distribution of anti-Soviet leaflets in different locations of the USSR; handwritten note re Brezhnev's request to pass on the memorandum to the members of the TsK KPSS Presidium, 1966 February-March (Opis 6, Reel 1.989, File 30)
  - Opis 7
    - Extract from the minutes of the TsK KPSS Politburo re procedures for participation of the Soviet Armed Forces in elections; draft resolution of the RSFSR Supreme Soviet; draft resolution of the TsK KPSS; memorandum to the TsK KPSS from N. Petrovichev, Deputy Chief of the Department of Organizational and Party Work, and N. Savinkin, Chief of the Department of Administrative Organs; memorandum to the TsK KPSS from D. Ustinov and A. Yepishev, 1982 February-March (Opis 7, Reel 1.989, File 1)
    - Extract from the minutes of the TsK KPSS Politburo re the procedure for issuing employees of Soviet institutions and organizations copies of legal documents relating to their personal rights; draft decree of the USSR Supreme Soviet; draft resolution of the USSR Council of Ministers, 1983 July (Opis 7, Reel 1.989, File 2)
    - Extract from the minutes of the TsK KPSS Politburo re increasing efforts to strengthen socialist labor discipline; extract from the resolution of the USSR Council of Ministers and the All-Union Central Council of Trade Unions, 1983 July (Opis 7, Reel 1.989, File 3)
    - Extract from the minutes of the TsK KPSS Politburo re the resolution of the 27th KPSS Congress and the directives of the political report presented to the Congress by the TsK KPSS; list of assignments (aimed to develop proposals improving effectiveness of prosecutors' control) issued in connection with the resolution, 1986 March (Opis 7, Reel 1.989, File 4)
    - Extract from the minutes of the TsK KPSS Politburo re the memoranda from V. Terebilov, Chairman of the USSR Supreme Court, and A. Rekunkov, Prosecutor General, on shortcomings in the crime prevention system; part of Terebilov's memorandum (the beginning is missing); memorandum to the TsK KPSS from A. Rekunkov re the arrest of the "very dangerous criminal" G. Mikhasevich, and re major violations of the socialist legal system against innocent people; memorandum from the RSFSR Deputy Prosecutor General re charges against Dukletin and others; memorandum from M. Gorbachev on capital punishment, 1986 April-May (Opis 7, Reel 1.989, File 5)
    - Extract from the minutes of the TsK KPSS Politburo re elections to local Soviets of people's deputies, 1986 October (Opis 7, Reel 1.989, File 6)
    - Extract from the minutes of the TsK KPSS Politburo re socialist law and order and protection of rights and interests of working people; memorandum to the TsK KPSS from top officials of the Council of Ministers, Supreme Court, and Prosecutor General's Office; resolution of the TsK KPSS, 1986 September-October (Opis 7, Reel 1.989, File 7)
    - Extract from the minutes of the TsK KPSS Politburo re socialist law and order, and protection of rights and interests of working people, 1986 November (Opis 7, Reel 1.989, File 8)
    - Extract from the minutes of the TsK KPSS Politburo re the directives of the TsK KPSS Plenum (January 1987) on perestroĭka and cadre policy, 1987 February (Opis 7, Reel 1.989, File 9)
    - Extract from the minutes of the TsK KPSS Politburo re elections to local Soviets of people's deputies, and elections of people's judges and people's jurors of courts in raions and cities; draft resolution of the Presidium of the RSFSR Supreme Soviet on experimental elections (with multiple candidates) to the local Soviets; memorandum from the Department of Organizational and Party Work, Propaganda Department, and Department of Administrative Organs re measures to be taken in respect to the elections; schedule of the election campaign, 1987 February (Opis 7, Reel 1.989, File 10)
    - Extract from the minutes of the TsK KPSS Politburo re analyses of elections to local Soviets of people's deputies and to people's courts; memorandum to the TsK KPSS from the Department of Organizational and Party Work, 1987 June-July (Opis 7, Reel 1.989, File 11)
    - Extract from the minutes of the TsK KPSS Politburo re improvement in the administration of the judicial system; memorandum to the TsK KPSS from V. Chebrikov, Chairman of the Committee for State Security (KGB), and A. Lukianov, Chairman of the Presidium of the USSR Supreme Soviet, 1987 October-December (Opis 7, Reel 1.989, File 12)
    - Extract from the minutes of the TsK KPSS Politburo re effectiveness of investigations, trials, and courts; draft decree of the USSR Supreme Court on amendments to the procedure for collecting child support; draft decree of the USSR Supreme Soviet on amendments to the RSFSR Criminal and Civil Codes; draft decree of the USSR Supreme Soviet on amendments to legislative acts; resolution of the USSR Supreme Soviet on measures to be taken to facilitate work of investigative, trial, and court systems; memorandum to the TsK KPSS from N. Savinkin, Chief of the Department of Administrative Organs, 1984 December - 1985 January (Opis 7, Reel 1.989, File 13)
    - Extract from the minutes of the TsK KPSS Politburo on establishing the USSR Association of Lawyers; memorandum to the TsK KPSS from B. Kravtsov and A. S. Pavlov, 1988 November-December (Opis 7, Reel 1.989, File 14)
    - Extract from the minutes of the TsK KPSS Politburo re the reorganization of military justice institutions; memorandum to the TsK KPSS from V. Chebrikov, Chairman of the KGB, 1989 January-February (Opis 7, Reel 1.989, File 15)
    - Extract from the minutes of the TsK KPSS Politburo re reform of the court system; memorandum to the TsK KPSS from the TsK KPSS Commission for Legal Policy; memorandum to the TsK KPSS from V. Shcherbitskii, Secretary of the Central Committee of the Communist Party of the Ukraine; memorandum to the TsK KPSS from A. S. Pavlov, Chief of the State and Legal Department, re letters and appeals of employees of court institutions in connection with working and living conditions; appeal to M. Gorbachev from members of the RSFSR Supreme Court (70 signatures), 1989 April-May (Opis 7, Reel 1.989, File 16)
    - Memorandum to M. Gorbachev, General Secretary of the TsK KPSS, from V. Chebrikov, Chairman of the KGB, re a meeting of the TsK KPSS Commission for Legal Policy; excerpt from the shorthand report of the Commission's meeting, 1989 April (Opis 7, Reel 1.989, File 17)
  - Opis 8
    - Record of the conference between V. Musatov, Chief of the TsK KPSS International Department, and the delegation of the Republic of Korea (South Korea) Parliament headed by Parliament member Kim Young Kwan(?), General Secretary of the Liberal-Democratic Party; three notes, 1991 July (Opis 8, Reel 1.990, File 1)
    - Memorandum to the TsK KPSS from V. Serebriakov, Acting Chief of the Political Department of Military Detachment 72004, re the new party structure in the Kamenskii garrison; extract from the minutes of the Kamenskii garrison communists' meeting, 1991 January (Opis 8, Reel 1.990, File 2)
    - Appeal to the TsK KPSS from Captain V. Narizhnyi, Deputy Secretary of the Black Sea Fleet (Chernomorskii Flot) Party Committee, re the convocation of the KPSS Extraordinary Congress; letter to the editorial staff of Pravda (Truth) newspaper and other official newspapers from G. Vinnichuk, Secretary of the Antiaircraft Troops KPSS Committee; memorandum to the TsK KPSS from V. Voronko, Deputy Chief of the Organizational Department; miscellaneous documents, 1991 June-July (Opis 8, Reel 1.990, File 3)
    - Summary of the discussion on the merger of the Legal Academy under the USSR Ministry of Justice and the Academy of Social and Political Sciences under the TsK KPSS into the Association of Social, Political, and Legal Sciences under the TsK KPSS Academy; memorandum to A. Dzasokhov from S. Lushchikov, Minister of Justice, 1990 January - 1991 April (Opis 8, Reel 1.990, File 4)
    - Appeal to M. Gorbachev from Major Postnikov, Secretary of the Regiment KPSS Bureau, re the situation in the Soviet Armed Forces; report to the TsK KPSS Secretary O. Shenin from N. Shliaga, Chief of the Main Political Directorate of the Soviet Armed Forces; memorandum to the TsK KPSS from I. Kovyrin, Deputy Chief of the Organizational Department; miscellaneous documents, 1990 December - 1991 April (Opis 8, Reel 1.990, File 5)
    - Memorandum to V. S. Pavlov, Prime Minister, from S. Lushchikov, Minister of Justice, re the review of Soviet legislation; resolution of the USSR Council of Ministers invalidating obsolete resolutions of the Soviet Government; memorandum of the TsK KPSS Law Department; memorandum to the TsK KPSS from A. S. Pavlov, Deputy Chief of the Department of Legislative Initiatives and Legal Affairs, 1991 February-July (Opis 8, Reel 1.990, File 6)
    - Memorandum to the TsK KPSS from G. Yagodin, Chairman of the State Committee for People's Education, re provision of education to the citizens of other countries in 1991; memorandum to the TsK KPSS International Department from V. Zubarev, Deputy Chairman of the State Committee for People's Education, re the cost of educating foreign students in the Soviet Union; memorandum to the TsK KPSS from V. Rykin, Deputy Chief of the International Department, re withholding KPSS scholarships from foreign students who were members of communist and workers' parties, 1991 February - May (Opis 8, Reel 1.990, File 7)
    - Memorandum to the TsK KPSS from V. Durasov, Deputy Chairman of the USSR State Committee for Planning (Gosplan), and V. Raevskii, Deputy Minister of Finance, re paper supplies to the Molodaia Gvardiia (Young Guards) publishing house;memorandum to P. Luchinskii, TsK KPSS Secretary, from V. Mishin, Deputy Administrator of the Administration of TsK KPSS Affairs; brief instructions, 1991 February-March (Opis 8, Reel 1.990, File 8)
    - Political Principles of the Liberal Democratic Party (Son Sann group of the Cambodian opposition), translated into Russian; cover letter from V. Mikhailov, Chief of the Main Intelligence Directorate of the General Staff, 1991 June (Opis 8, Reel 1.990, File 9)
    - Memorandum to the TsK KPSS from I. Skiba, Chief of the Department of Agrarian Policy, re agricultural resources, with a press release from the USSR State Committee for Statistics (Goskomstat); miscellaneous items, 1991 July (Opis 8, Reel 1.990, File 10)